Welcome everyone to today's presentation on artificial intelligence and machine learning.
I'm excited to share with you some of the latest developments in this rapidly evolving field.
Let's start by looking at this diagram that shows the relationship between AI, machine learning, and deep learning.
As you can see here, artificial intelligence is the broader field that encompasses machine learning as a subset.
Machine learning, in turn, includes deep learning as one of its most powerful techniques.
Now, let's examine this chart that shows the growth of AI applications across different industries.
Healthcare leads the way with a 45% adoption rate, followed by finance at 38%.
The transportation industry is also showing significant growth, particularly with autonomous vehicles.
Moving on to the technical aspects, let's look at this neural network architecture diagram.
This shows a typical deep learning model with input layers, hidden layers, and output layers.
Each node in these layers performs specific computations that contribute to the overall learning process.
Here's an example of how this works in practice with image recognition tasks.
The model learns to identify features at different levels of abstraction.
Starting with simple edges and shapes in the early layers, moving to complex objects in deeper layers.
Let's now discuss the challenges and limitations of current AI systems.
One major challenge is the need for large amounts of high-quality training data.
Another significant issue is the interpretability of AI decisions, especially in critical applications.
Looking ahead, here are some exciting developments we can expect in the coming years.
Quantum machine learning promises to solve problems that are currently computationally intractable.
Thank you for your attention. I'll now take questions about any of the topics we've covered today.